<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: internet-radio, | Pragmatic Development Notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://pragdevnotes.com/blog/categories/internet-radio/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pragdevnotes.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-09T23:53:31+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://pragdevnotes.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Boško Ivanišević]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RStreamTuner in action]]></title>
    <link href="http://pragdevnotes.com/blog/2010/01/26/rstreamtuner-in-action/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-26T19:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://pragdevnotes.com/blog/2010/01/26/rstreamtuner-in-action</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friend of mine criticised me why I didn’t put some screenshots on <a href="http://github.com/bosko/rstreamtuner">project page</a>. Since I couldn’t find a way to do it there I’ve decided to put some screenshots here, so
here they are.</p>

<p><img src="/images/rst-screenshots/rst_xiph.png" title="RST Xiph plugin." >
<img src="/images/rst-screenshots/rst_search.png" title="RST SHOUTcast search in action" >
<img src="/images/rst-screenshots/rst_preferences.png" title="RST plugin preferences." ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RStreamTuner - new streaming directories browser]]></title>
    <link href="http://pragdevnotes.com/blog/2010/01/22/rstreamtuner-new-streaming-directories-browser/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-22T19:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://pragdevnotes.com/blog/2010/01/22/rstreamtuner-new-streaming-directories-browser</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I like to listen various Internet radio stations while I work. My favourite application was
<a href="http://www.nongnu.org/streamtuner">streamtuner</a> mostly because it had support for SHOUTcast. Unluckily new SHOUTcast design cannot be handled by <strong>streamtuner</strong> and future development on this application is
stopped. In other words there is a little chance for streamtuner to be upgraded so I’ve decided to make my own streaming directories browser &ndash; <a href="http://github.com/bosko/rstreamtuner">RStreamTuner (Ruby Stream Tuner)</a>.</p>

<p>As usual developing in Ruby was real pleasure and only doubt was what to use for GUI part. I’ve started with Ruby/Tk and left it very quickly due to very poor documentation (and probably lack of Tcl knowledge). I had
to find replacement and my primary goal was to find library that works equally well on Linux and Windows. WxWidgets with WxRuby gem was my final choice. Although <strong>RStreamTuner</strong> is still in early development
phase it is quite usable. At the moment it supports SHOUTcast and Xiph directories, but I plan to add more as soon as I find good one. Good candidate could be Live365 but they’ve made their pages quite hard to
parse so I’ll probably leave it for later.</p>

<p>Once I reach beta version, making support for new streaming directories will be quite easy and will require implementation of just a few methods. As a matter of act it is already so simple but I’m not
satisfied with the code and will change it once I find a little bit more time. Code is quite rough (I had little time to make <strong>RStreamTuner</strong> and was eager to get working version as soon as possible). Besides I
want to write detailed instructions how to add support for new directories. Anyway if you like to listen Internet radion stations and like Ruby clone <a href="http://github.com/bosko/rstreamtuner">RStreamTuner</a>. Of
course if you have suggestions do not hasitate to drop me a note and if you make support for new streaming directory just send me a pull request and I’ll try to grab it as soon as possible.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
